The subnet mask for an IP address defines the network portion and the host portion of an IP address. To demonstrate, take a look at this IP address and subnet mask.
The IP address is 10.0.2.46 with a subnet mask of 255.255.255.0. The 255s represent the network portion of the IP address, which in this case is 10.0.2.
The 0 in the subnet mask represents the host portion of the IP address, which will be different for every device on this network.
According to this subnet mask, then, in this network, all devices will start with an IP address of 10.0.2 and end with a different number, that number being 0 to 255.
Technically, the first and last IP addresses in a range are reserved for the network address and broadcast address,
respectively, so the number ranges available for devices in this subnet would be 1 to 254.
If the subnet mask were 255.255.0.0, the 10.0 portion would be the host portion and you could have 256 x 256 -2 = 65,534 devices on the network.
If the subnet mask were 255.0.0.0, the 10 portion would be the host portion and you could have 256 x 256 x 256 -2 = 16,777,214 devices on the network
Do those numbers sound familiar? They should, because we covered this in the addressing topic earlier in this section.
Summing this up, the main purpose of a subnet mask is to determine the size of a subnet within a network.